# Anastasis Kratsios

Geometric Deep Learning for Mathematical Finance

University of Basel Department of Mathematics and Computer Science Spiegelgasse 1 4051 Basel Switzerland (a) (+41) 78 933 99 19

#### Profile

Specialization: I introduce and study universally deep learning models capable of leveraging geometric structures in mathematical finance and data science problems.

**Expertise (Mathematics):** Approximation theory, mathematical finance, geometric topology, optimal transport, analysis on metric spaces.

Expertise (Data Science): Geometric deep learning, deep learning, meta-learning.

# Employment History

#### Academic

2021-Current Postdoctoral Researcher - Geometric Deep Learning, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland.

- Select Contributions:
  - First neural network architecture capable of universal approximation with exact con-
  - First deep neural version of Berge's Maximum Theorem (1963) with exact constraint satisfaction.
- O Co-supervision: Doctoral Student T. Liu
  - Completed Collaboration (Numerical Part): Universal Approximation under constraints is possible with transformers.
  - Working Paper: Generalization bounds for random feature models between Banach, supporting Schauder basises, when data-generating distribution is supported on an unknown manifold,
- Ongoing Research:
  - Adapted universal approximation of stochastic processes by recurrent transformer networks - B. Acciaio and G. Pammer (ETH Math. Finance) - Expected Dec.  $1^{rst}$ ,
  - PAC-Bayesian Bounds in Function Space P. Kassraie and J. Rothfuss (ETH Comp. Sci.) - Expected January  $15^{th}$ ,
  - Canonical Quantitative Universal Approximators for General Metric Spaces M. Lassas (U. Helsinki), M. de Hoop (Rice U.) - Expected March  $1^{rst}$ .

# 2018-2021 Postdoctoral Researcher - Stochastic Finance and Geometric Deep Learning, ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland

- Select contributions:
  - Introduced the first (quantitative) universal approximation theorems for general inputoutput spaces,
  - Developed the first universal approximator from the space of Gaussian measures with Wasserstein metric, to itself,
  - Developed the first meta-optimization procedure for learning regret-optimal gradientdescent algorithms,
  - Developed the first penalty for arbitrage-free machine learning in finance,
  - Proved first deterministic universal classification theorems,
  - Introduce meta-algorithm for generating optimal UAP-invariant feature maps,
  - Developed an architecture capable of uniformly approximating discontinuous functions,

- Obtained the first characterization of the universal approximation property.
- Supervision:
  - Guide: L. Papon (Master's Student from EPFL),
  - Master's Semester Project: An Overview of Risk-Averse Valuation.
  - Student: Nikolaos Mourdoukoutas.

# 2014-2015 Lecturer, Concordia University, Montreal, Canada.

- Transferred my intuition to new students in the field,
- Framed classical theory in the context of modern applications; such as data-science examples to motivate linear algebraic ideas,
- Provided extended lectures outside of requirements to help students go beyond their requirements and succeed in their exams.

#### Private Sector

# 2017 Risk Management Research, CIBC Capital Markets, Toronto, Canada

- Modelled for non-modellable risk-factors for the FRTB under Basel III,
- Developed clustering based model selection methodology for liquid bonds proxying,
- Part of the team working on stochastic filtering-based methods for predicting IPO prices.
- Developed algorithms for Bloomberg to R interphasing.

# Outreach

# 2016–2017 Mathematics Educator for Students with Learning Disabilities, Epsilon Learning Center, Toronto (Leslieville), Canada.

- Tutored 6-13 year old students with learning disabilities,
- Help to discover and overcome each student's learning barriers,
- Identified personalized learning tools (e.g. visual, analytic, mechanical, etc..) helping each student best connect to the material,
- Helped build student's "mathematical self-confidence".

# Education

# 2014–2018 PhD Mathematical Finance, Concordia University, Montreal

- Thesis: Arbitrage-free Regularization, Geometric Learning, And Non-Euclidean Filtering In Finance.
- Contributions:
  - Developed the NEU meta-algorithm, a procedure which learns an optimal loss function given a learning task and a data-set,
  - Applied the NEU meta-algorithm to stock prediction and yield-curve dimensionality reduction tasks,
  - Introduced no-arbitrage penalty in the generalized HJM framework and used it to learn arbitrage-free forward-rate curve models,
  - Introduced a non-Euclidean filtering algorithm for Cartan-Hadamard spaces and used it to predict efficient portfolios.
- Research Groups: Quantact and Montreal Analysis Seminar.

# 2012–2014 MSc Pure Mathematics, University of Montreal, Montreal

- Thesis: Bounding The Hochschild Cohomological Dimension
- Major Contributions:
  - Developed a lower-bound on the Hochschild cohomological dimension for any K-algebra,
  - Used this lower-bound to show that most commutative  $\mathbb{K}\text{-algebras}$  fail to be smooth.
- Research Groups: CIRGET, Graduate Students Seminar in Mathematics.

# Research Articles

#### **Publications**

2021 **NEU: A Meta-Algorithm for Universal UAP-Invariant Feature Representa- tion**, (JMLR) The Journal of Machine Learning Research.

Joint work with: C. Hyndman

2021 Optimizing Optimizers: Regret-optimal gradient descent algorithms, (COLT)  $34^{th}$  Conference on Learning Theory.

Joint work with: P. Casgrain

2021 **The Universal Approximation Property**, Annals of Mathematics and Artificial Intelligence.

2020 **Non-Euclidean Universal Approximation**, (NeurIPS) 33<sup>th</sup> - Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems.

Joint work with: I. Bilokopytov

2020 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization**, Risks - Special Issue on Machine Learning in Finance, Insurance and Risk Management.

Joint work with: C. Hyndman

2020 **The Entropic Measure Transform**, Canadian Journal of Statistics - Special Issue: Special Issue on Stochastic Models, Statistics, and Finance.

Joint work with: C. Hyndman and R. Wang

2021 Lower-Estimates on the Hochschild (Co)Homological Dimension of Commutative Algebras and Applications to Smooth Affine Schemes and Quasi-Free Algebras, Mathematics - Special Issue: New Trends in Algebraic Geometry and Its Applications.

#### **Under Review**

2021 Universal Approximation Under Constraints is Possible with Transformers, *ArXiV: 2110.03303*.

Joint work with: I. Dokmanic, T. Liu, and B. Zamanlooy

2021 Universal Approximation Theorems for Geometric Deep Learning, *ArXiV*: 2101.05390.

Joint work with: L. Papon

- 2021 Universal Regular Conditional Distributions via Probability Measure-Valued Deep Neural Models, *ArXiV*: 2105.07743.
- 2021 Learning Sub-Patterns in Piece-Wise Continuous Functions, *ArXiV:* 2010.15571.

Joint work with: B. Zamanlooy

Denise: Deep Robust Principal Component Analysis for Positive Semidefinite Matrices, ArXiV: 2004.13612.
 Joint work with: J. Teichmann, P. Ruyssen, C. Herrera, and F. Krach

2021 A Canonical Transform for Strengthening the Local  $L^p$ -Type Universal Approximation Property, ArXiV: 2006.14378.

Joint work with: B. Zamanlooy

# White Papers

- 2017 **Replication of a Real-Estate Market Index (Teranet)**, Proceedings: Proceedings: Eighth Montreal Industrial Problem Solving Workshop.
- 2014 Hochschild Cohomological Dimension is Not Upper Semi-Continuous, *Note. ArXiV: 1407.4825.*

# Conferences and Talks

- 2021 Geometric Deep Learning for High-Dimensional Option Pricing and Constrained Approximation, AIMS Lab Seminar, McMaster University, Hamilton, Canada
- 2021 Universal Approximation with Exact Constraint Satisfaction is Possible with Transformers, Talks in Financial and Insurance Mathematics, ETH Zürich
- 2021 **Universal Probability Measure-Valued Deep Neural Networks**, *Probability Days*, University of Mannheim (Remote)
- 2021 Optimizing Optimizers: Regret-optimal gradient descent algorithms, *COLT* 2021, Boulder, Colorado (Remote)
- 2021 **Quantitative Non-Euclidean Universal Approximation**, *ML Explained Aggregate Intellect Al.Science*, Online, Toronto, Canada (Remote)
- 2021 Universal Probability Measure-Valued Deep Neural Networks , Quantact (CRM), Montreal, Canada,
- 2020 **Non-Euclidean Universal Approximation**, 34<sup>th</sup> NeurlPS 2020, Online, NA
- 2020 Universal Feature Map Generation, ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland
- 2020 Limit Orderbook Geometry and Arbitrage-Free Volume Adjustments, Imperial College, London, United Kingdom Invited by: Damiano Brigo
- 2019 NEU Meta-Learning, Universal Approximation Properties, and Learning Model-Free Loss-Functions, ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland
- 2019 **Universal Approximation Theorems**, *Concordia Data Science Seminar*, Montreal, Canada.
- 2019 **A Universal Feature Space**, 12<sup>th</sup> Freiburg-Wien-Zürich (FWZ) Seminar, Zürich, Switzerland.

- 2019 **Universal Approximation Theorems**, Österreichische Mathematische Gesellschaft Conference 2019, Dornbirn, Austria.
- 2019 **Universal Approximation Theorems**, *Vienna Congress on Mathematical Finance VCMF 2019*, Vienna, Austria.
- 2019 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization**, 10<sup>th</sup> Freiburg-Wien-Zürich (FWZ) Seminar, Vienne, Autstria.
- 2019 **Risk-Averse Conditional Expectation and Shortfall-Regression**, *ETH Zürich*, Zürich, Switzerland.
- 2018 Geometric Learning and Filtering in Finance ,  $10^{th}$  Bachelier World Congres, Dublin, Ireland.
- 2018 Arbitrage-Free Regularization,  $10^{th}$  Bachelier World Congres, Dublin, Ireland.
- 2018 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization**,  $5^{th}$  Workshop on Insurance Mathematics with a Special Session on Big-Data and Machine Learning in Risk Management , Montreal, Canada.
- 2017 A Geometric Approach to Arbitrage-Free Modeling, Estimation, and Prediction, International Conference on Mathematical Finance, Waterloo, Canada. Presentation by coauthor.
- 2017 **Geometric Learning and Non-Euclidean Filtering in Finance**, Canadian Mathematical Society Winter Meeting, Waterloo, Canada.
- 2017 A Geometric Approach to Arbitrage-Free Modeling, Estimation, and Prediction, 11<sup>th</sup> Bachelier Colloquium on Mathematical Finance and Stochastic Calculus, Métabief, France.
  Presentation by coauthor.
- 2016 Manifold Learning Algorithms for Arbitrage-Free Low-Dimensional on-Linear Model Selection, Pacific Institute for the Mathematical Sciences (PIMS); High-Frequency Trading Workshop, Edmonton, Canada.
- 2016 A Geometric Approach to Arbitrage-Free Modeling, Estimation, and Prediction, Canadian Mathematical Society Winter Meeting, Niagra, Canada. Presentation by coauthor.
- 2016 Manifold learning algorithms for arbitrage-free low-dimensional nonlinear model selection, AMS - AMS Fall Meeting, Brunswick, USA. Presentation by coauthor.
- 2016 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization for Forward Rates**, *ENCS Data Science Research Centre*, Montreal, Canada.

# Extracurricular Activities

# Academic Community

- 2018–present Weekly Geometric Deep Learning Seminar, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland.
  - $\circ$  Give feedback and guide  $3^{rd}$  of PhD students in same area,
  - Invite Speakers and possible group collaborators,
  - Organize seminar.

- 2018–2021 **Organiser of the Weekly Financial and Insurance Mathematics Seminar**, *ETH Zürich*, Zürich, Switzerland.
  - o Organize the weekly seminar,
  - Align schedules with international researchers,
  - Author the weekly news bulletin.
- 2017–2018 **Vice-President Mathematics and Statistics Graduate Students Association**, *Concordia University*, Montreal, Canada.
  - o Organised student social events and outings,
  - Helped maintain graduate student's positive morale by introducing a free coffee system.